Guide to the Brownsville and East New York Photographs, 1958-1965 BCMS.0044
Brooklyn Collection
Brownsville and East New York Photographs, 1958-1965
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0044
0.2 Linear feet in 1 document box.
99 black and white photographic prints of the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Brownsville and East New York dated 1958-1965.
Scope and Contents
99 black and white photographic prints.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
Purchased from Brian Merlis in 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series by neighborhood. Within each series, the photographs are arranged chronologically.
Historical Note
Brownsville and East New York are adjoining neighborhoods in the eastern part of Brooklyn, New York. While it can be difficult to definitively state the borders of neighborhoods, Brownsville is often roughly considered to be bounded by Eastern Parkway to the north, Ralph Avenue/E. 98th Street to the west, Linden Boulevard to the south, and the elevated subway tracks between Junius Street and Van Sinderen Avenue to the east. East New York's boundaries are roughly located at Cypress Hills Cemetery to the north, the elevated rail tracks next to Van Sinderen Avenue to the west, Jamaica Bay to the south, and the Queens County line to the east. The photos in this collection also include images of Ocean Hill, a smaller neighborhood to the north of Brownsville with which Brownsville is often associated.
Both of these neighborhoods experienced profound shifts during the period depicted in these photographs. In the early twentieth century, this part of Brooklyn was largely populated by working class European immigrants. Due to the development of several New York City Housing Authority (NYCHA) housing projects in both neighborhoods, as well as changing immigration policies in the United States, the neighborhood demographics shifted midcentury to primarily African-American and Hispanic residents.
The photos in this collection primarily depict street scenes, which often include distinctive vehicles such as buses or police cars. There are also images of the residents of these communities which give a glimpse of their demographic makeup. Many local businesses appear in these photographs as well.
Related Materials
Books about Brownsville at the Brooklyn Collection
Books about East New York at the Brooklyn Collection
Brooklyn Collection clippings files on East New York and Brownsville
Brooklyn Eagle Photos: multiple headings for Brownsville and East New York
Ephemera Collection: headings for Brownsville and East New York
Automobiles; Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ocean Hill (New York, N.Y.); Photographs; Police vehicles; Streets
- Brownsville
  - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rockaway and Lott Avenues, 4/21/1958
    - Newport Street between Amboy Street and Herzl Street, 4/26/1958; (2 photographs)
    - Sutter Avenue from Thatford Avenue, 5/12/1958
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pitkin Avenue west from Sackman Street, 1/27/1959
    - Chester Street from Riverdale Avenue, 11/2/1959
    - Riverdale Avenue from Chester Street, 11/2/1959
  - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sackman Street between Pitkin and Belmont Avenues
    - Thatford and Pitkin Avenues
    - Feldman Lumber, Dumont and Hopkinson Avenues (now Thomas S. Boyland Street)
    - Police car, Pitkin and Thatford Avenues
  - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard) south toward Pitkin Avenue, 5/9/1962; (2 photographs)
    - Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard) north to Pitkin Avenue, 5/9/1962
    - Chester Street between Pitkin and Sutter Avenues, 5/13/1962; (2 photographs)
    - Dumont Avenue toward Chester Street, 5/22/1962
    - Dumont Avenue and Chester Street, 5/22/1962
    - Christopher and Lott Avenues, 10/24/1962; (3 photographs)
    - Bristol Street toward Sutter Avenue, 10/27/1962
    - Riverdale Avenue east from East 98th Street, 12/1/1962
    - Police car, Blake Avenue to Strauss Street
    - Blake Avenue to Strauss Street
    - Police car, Chester Street to Blake Avenue
  - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Blake Avenue from Powell Street, 4/17/1963
    - Blake Avenue and Powell Street, 4/17/1963; (2 photographs)
    - Powell Street from Blake Avenue, 4/17/1963
    - Amboy Street toward Blake Avenue, 4/23/1963
    - Junius Street to Sutter Avenue, 4/26/1963
    - Sutter Avenue east toward Junius Street, 4/26/1963
    - Powell Street and Glenmore Avenue, 7/30/1963
    - Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard) south from Pitkin Avenue, 9/7/1963
    - Pitkin Avenue east from Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 9/7/1963
    - Rockaway Parkway south from East New York Avenue, 9/8/1963; (2 photographs)
    - Pitkin Avenue east from Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 9/7/1963
    - Pitkin Avenue and Grafton Street/Zion Park, 11/17/1963; (4 photographs)
    - Newport Street from Saratoga Avenue, 12/6/1963
    - Saratoga Avenue north from Newport Street, 12/6/1963
    - Police car, Riverdale Avenue to Christopher Avenue
    - Subway elevated tracks, Livonia Avenue and Chester Street
    - Powell Street near Sutter Avenue
    - Crowd at Dumont Avenue and Saratoga Avenue
    - Saratoga Avenue north from Dumont Avenue
    - Police car outside bowling alley, Linden Boulevard from Rockaway Avenue
    - Feldman Lumber, Dumont Avenue and Hopkinson Avenue (now Thomas S. Boyland Street)
    - Christopher and Riverdale Avenues
    - Powell Street and Glenmore Avenues
    - Dumont Avenue west to Hopkinson Avenue (now Thomas S. Boyland Street)
    - Bus outside P.S. 275, Rickaway Avenue and Linden Bouelvard
    - Dumont Avenue west to Saratoga Avenue
  - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chester Street and Sutter Avenue, 1/2/1964
    - Strauss Street to Dumont Avenue, 3/6/1964
    - Dumont Avenue west to Strauss Street, 3/6/1964
    - Amboy Street near Sutter Avenue, 3/20/1964
    - 121 Amboy Street, near Sutter Avenue, 3/20/1964
    - Pitkin Avenue east to Hopkinson Avenue (now Thomas S. Boyland Street)
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dean Street and Howard Avenue, Ocean Hill
    - Fulton Street and Rockway Avenue, Ocean Hill
    - Newport Street west to Saratoga Avenue
    - Newport Street east to Saratoga Avenue
    - Pitkin and Stone Avenues (now Mother Gaston Boulevard)
    - Lott Avenue west from Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard)
    - P.S. 184, Lott and Stone Avenues (now Mother Gaston Boulevard)
    - Saratoga Avenue from Newport Street
    - Riverdale Avenue south to Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard)
    - People on public housing bench
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Police car, Eastern Parkway and Sterling Place
- East New York
  - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Liberty Avenue and Wyona Street, 4/22/1958
    - Liberty Avenue and Chestnut Street, 5/1/1958
    - Essex Street to Dumont Avenue, 5/4/1958
    - Essex Street between Liberty and Atlantic Avenues, 5/13/1958
    - Liberty Avenue west to Hinsdale Street, 6/2/1958
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Vermont Street and Belmont Avenue, 1/11/1959
    - Crescent and Fulton Streets, 4/2/1959
    - Blake Avenue and Essex Street, 4/29/1959
    - Glenmore Avenue west to Ashford Street, 5/25/1959
    - Jerome Street to Pitkin Avenue, 10/10/1959
    - Pennsylvania and Riverdale Avenues, 11/14/1959
  - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Man at Vermont Street and Stanley Avenue, 5/13/1962
    - Vermont Street near Atlantic Avenue, 5/23/1962
    - Alabama Avenue from Riverdale Avenue, 10/24/1962
    - Alabama Avenue to Riverdale Avenue, 10/24/1962
  - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Montauk Avenue to Pitkin Avenue, 7/2/1963
    - Arlington Avenue to Jerome Street, 11/7/1963
  - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ridgewood Avenue at Force Tube Avenue, 1/10/1964
    - Jamaica Avenue west to Force Tube Avenue, 1/10/1964
    - Belmont Avenue toward Hemlock Street, 2/15/1964
    - Hemlock Street toward Belmont Avenue, 2/15/1964
    - Sutter Avenue east from Van Sinderen Avenue, 2/26/1964
    - Jamaica Avenue east to Miller Avenue, 3/20/1964
    - Synagogue, Alabama Avenue north to Dumont Avenue, 7/28/1964
    - Fortunoff's, Alabama Avenue at Livonia Avenue, 7/28/1964